<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>computer-networks on schoettkr</title>
    <link>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/tags/computer-networks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in computer-networks on schoettkr</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/tags/computer-networks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Networks - Lecture 05</title>
      <link>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/05-lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/05-lecture/</guid>
      <description>Modems Modem = MOdulator/DEmodulator
 basieren urspruenglich uaf der klassischen Teilnehmeranschlussleitung des Fernsprechnetzes     Leistungsanschaltung = signaltechnische (Sende- und Empfangs-) Verstaerkung der zu uebertragenen Signale Modulationsteil = Modulation/Demodulation (zB Amplitude, Frequenz, &amp;hellip;)  Modulation beschreibt einen Vorgang, bei dem ein zu uebertragendes Nutzsignal einen sog. Traeger veraendert (moduliert), dadurch wird eine hochfrequente Uebertragung des niederfrequenten Nutzsignals ermoeglicht die Nachricht wird empfangsseitig durch einen Demodulator zurueck gewonnen, beispielsweise um ein Audiosignal in UKW-Empfaengern aus dem hochfrequenten, frequenzmodulierten Signal (87,5-108 MHz) zurueckzugewinnen (Radio)  Steuer-/Meldeteil = Analyse der vom Netz kommenden Dienstsignale, An-/Abschaltung des Modems an Steuerfunktionen (zB Betriebs-, Sendebereitschaft)  Mehrfachnutzung von Medien Multiplexverfahren (lat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Networks - Lecture 04</title>
      <link>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/04_lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/04_lecture/</guid>
      <description>Signals and Bit Transmission Introduction Data Transmission - Bit to Signal to Bit:
 sits directly on the physical medium (eg cable) Layer 1 in the ISO/OSI and Internet Reference (TCP/IP) Model transmission of unstructured bit sequences via physical medium data transmission entails the physical connection and the conversion between data &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; signals there are norms for interfaces (especially for physical interfaces)  Signals and their Parameters A signal is a state or a modification of material systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Networks - Lecture 03</title>
      <link>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/03_lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/03_lecture/</guid>
      <description>Basic model of (tele)communication    participants act either as a sender or receiver usage of the service occurs at a special interface (API) and by using a service address point the medium bridges the spatial (raeumlich) distance  The following image shows a layer model which shows the reduction of deficits from bottom to top:
There are certain principles to structure communication. These principles are also called communication protocols or short protocols and define a set of rules which communication between two or more parties has to follow/obey.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Networks - Lecture 02</title>
      <link>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/02_lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/02_lecture/</guid>
      <description>Back to the roots of the Internet
The internet consists of
 a set of computers which  use the same network protocol (TCP/IP) are somehow (directly or indirectly) connected to each other offer or use certain services  a set of (human or technical) users which access and use services and a set of further networks accessible via gateways  The most commonly used Internet services are:
 World Wide Web (www)  platform for hypermedial information exchange based on the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP)  Email  exchange of multimedial messages based on the Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP)  File Exchange  access and transmission of files based on File Transfer Protocol (FTP)  Network Management  surveillance and control of connected systems based on Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)   Model of a simple transmission system:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Networks - Lecture 01</title>
      <link>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/01_lecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://schoettkr.github.io/knowledge-database/uni/cn/01_lecture/</guid>
      <description>This was the first lecture in the new summer semester and therefore it was mostly about organizational stuff. Here are the most important points:
 the exam is gonna be a written one and might be open-book the start of the tutorials will be announced on the course website sometime in April (registration via opal) there are gonna be exercises to hand in  those can be found here  the main programming language used will be python  Fundamental literature:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>